this video is going to be an updated
version to an earlier video that i
created on projectile motion but let's
go over some basics the first thing you
need to know are the kinematic equations
at constant speed
d
is equal to vt displacement is equal to
velocity multiplied by the time now
under constant acceleration
displacement is equal to the average
velocity
multiplied by time and the average
is basically the average of the initial
and the final velocity you add up the
initial and the final and you divide it
by two if the acceleration is constant
now you also have some other equations
v final is equal to v initial plus a t
so the final velocity is equal to the
initial velocity plus the acceleration
multiplied by the time
also
the square of the final velocity is
equal to the square of the initial
velocity
plus two times the product of the
acceleration
and the displacement
and there's another equation
displacement is equal to v initial t
plus
one half
a t squared
now the displacement
is the change in position
it can be the final position
minus the initial position along the x
axis
or it can be along the y axis
so if we replace d
with
y final
minus y initial
we can get another equation that
perhaps you've seen in your physics
course by now
which looks like this the final position
is equal to the initial position
plus v initial t
plus one half
a t squared
now d can represent displacement or
sometimes you can use it to
find distance
distance and displacement are the same
if the object moves in one direction and
doesn't change direction
whenever the object changes direction
displacement and distance are different
so you got to be careful in what you
solve it but if it's moving in one
direction distance and displacement
they're the same in that case
now let's see if we have a ball
and we're gonna
kick it off the ground goes up and then
it's going to go down
gravitational acceleration
is negative 9.8
meters per second squared
for this example we're going to round it
and we're going to use
negative 10 just to keep things simple
so let's say at t equals zero i'm going
to put the time inside the ball
let's say the horizontal velocity v x
we're going to say it's 7
and the vertical velocity v y
we're going to say it's sturdy
now one second later
what do you think
the horizontal and the vertical velocity
will be
what about two seconds later
and then three seconds later
and so forth
so one second later
i should probably put that in a
different color
the horizontal velocity will not change
it's going to remain 7.
the vertical velocity will change
and how much will the vertical velocity
change by
the vertical velocity changes by the
gravitational acceleration acceleration
tells you how much the velocity changes
every second
since the gravitational acceleration
which is the acceleration in the y
direction
it changes about 10 every second
v y is going to decrease by 10 every
second so one second later it's going to
be 20.
two seconds later
the v x is going to be the same but v y
is going to be 10
three seconds later
v y is now zero at the top it's not
going up anymore you only have
horizontal motion
but v x is still seven
then v y becomes negative
the v x will always remain seven
because v x is constant the acceleration
in the x direction is zero
a projectile by definition
is only under the influence of gravity
so if you throw a pen once you release
it from your hand its projectile
a flying bird is not a projectile
its any air but
it has the force
generated by its wings acted on it so
it's not a projectile
projectiles
can only have gravity acting on it air
resistance is ignored
so this is going to be 2 3
4 seconds later
v y
is going to be
negative 10
5 seconds later
negative twenty
six seconds later negative thirty
now here's a question for you
what is the vertical velocity and the
speed five seconds later
the vertical velocity
v y
is negative 20.
the speed
is positive 20.
speed is the absolute value of velocity
velocity can be positive or negative
speed is always positive
speed is the magnitude of velocity
speed is a scalar quantity velocity is a
vector vectors have magnitude and
direction scalar quantities only have
magnitude only
now if you notice because the
acceleration is negative
the velocity
is always decreasing
on the left side it goes from 30 to zero
so it's decreasing on the right side
from zero to negative 30 it's still
decreasing
so the velocity is always decreasing
however the speed
because it's never negative
it's positive on the left side and the
right side
so notice that the speed
is decreasing
on the left side
but on the right side it's increasing
because it goes from 0
to 30.
so whenever the ball
travels upward
the velocity decreases
and the speed decreases but as the ball
begins to fall back down to the ground
or towards the earth
the speed increases and the velocity
continues to decrease
make sure you understand that
now there's three types of trajectories
that you need to be familiar with
so here's the first one
let's say if we have a ball that rolls
off a cliff
and it falls down
h represents the height of the cliff
r is the range
which is the horizontal distance
between the base of the cliff which is
here
and where the ball lands
now because it's moving horizontally
initially the initial speed is v x and
not v
well v and v x are the same
but
the initial speed is v x
at the top whenever it's moving
horizontally v y is equal to zero
as in the case of the other uh problem
so you can easily find the height using
this equation h equals one-half ac
squared
it comes from this equation
now because height is a vertical
displacement
everything in this equation that we use
has to be in the y direction
so we need to use d y vertical
displacement
v y initial
times t plus one half
a y t squared
now d y
is basically the height
at the top v y is zero so this term
disappears and so you get this equation
so make sure you know this equation
h equals one half ac squared is very
useful for this type of trajectory
now if you wish to calculate the range
it's equal to v x t
remember we said that whenever an object
moves with constant speed
d is equal to v t
now v x
is v cosine theta
and v y
is v sine theta
it's based on this triangle here's v
v x
and here's v y and here's the angle
theta
now according to
sohcahtoar perhaps you've seen this if
you've taken trig
s stands for sine
sine theta
is equal to
o and h stands for opposite and
hypotenuse so sine theta is the ratio
between the side that's opposite
to theta which is v y
divided by the sine that's
the hypotenuse which is across the box
and that's v
cosine theta
is equal to the adjacent side vx
divided by the hypotenuse of v
tangent theta
is equal to the opposite side which is v
y divided by the adjacent side v x
so from this equation
if you multiply both sides by v
you can see that v y
is v sine theta
now for the second equation
if you do the same thing v x is v sine
theta
now for the third equation it's useful
to calculate the angle
if tangent theta is v y over v x
then the angle theta
is the inverse tangent of v y divided by
v x
now according to the
pythagorean theorem
there's one more equation that we can
write
since
v x v y and v
are all the three sides in a right
triangle
and according to pythagorean theorem c
squared equals a squared plus b squared
v squared is equal to v x squared plus v
y squared
therefore v
is the square root of v x squared plus
v y squared
if you need to find a final speed just
before it hits the ground
this is the equation that you'll need
now let's talk about the second
trajectory that you'll see
which occurs when a ball is kicked off
from the ground it goes up and then goes
back down
this is going to be the height
or the maximum height of the trajectory
and the horizontal distance is the range
let's call this point a
b
and point c
now if you need to find the time it
takes
to go from point a to point b
it's equal to
v sine theta
divided by g
in another video i show you how you can
derive these equations
now the time it takes to go from
let's say a to c
is simply twice the value
from a to b
due to the symmetry of the graph
so you get this equation
now the maximum height is equal to v
squared
sine squared theta divided by 2g
the range is equal to v squared
sine 2 theta
divided by g
so because the velocity
the ball is kicked at an angle
you can be given v instead of v x or v y
and
the angle relative to the horizontal is
theta
so typically in a problem like this
you'll be given the initial speed any
angle and you could find anything you
need
based on these equations
now the other equations still apply
now it's important to understand that
the speed at part a or point a is the
same as the speed at point c
if you recall
when i went over the trajectory that
looks like this
with all the speeds every second
the speed one second later
was equal to the speed that
occurred at the same height
i think in the last example one second
later the vertical speed was 20 and on
the right side the vertical velocity was
negative 20 which means the speed was
also 20. two seconds later we had 10 and
10.
but as you can see
whenever you have two points at the same
height
the speed will be the same
so if you need to find the final speed
at point c is the same as the initial
speed at point a
just keep in mind at point a the
vertical velocity is positive but at
point c it's negative
but the magnitudes are the same
now the last trajectory
that
you need to be familiar with
looks like this typically you have a
ball
at a cliff or at a building
and it's kicked off at an angle it goes
up and then it goes back down
so all of the equations that you've seen
before
you can apply it
to this trajectory
now in addition to the other equations
one equation that might be useful
is this equation y final equals y
initial
plus
v y initial t
plus one half a t squared or a y t
squared where a y is negative 9.8
y initial
is basically the height of the cliff
and if you want to find the time it
takes to hit the ground that is at point
c
y final replace with zero and then use
the quadratic equation to get the answer
now typically you'll be given the
velocity v
and the angle theta so to find v y
v y is v sine theta so just keep that in
mind
now to use the quadratic formula
make sure you have a zero on one side of
the equation
t
is going to be equal to negative b
plus or minus the square root
b squared minus four 4ac
divided by 2a
now if you don't want to use the
quadratic formula
to find the time it takes to go from a
to c
you can find the time it takes to go
from a to b and add it from b to c
the time it takes to go from a to b we
have that formula
it's going to be 2v sine theta
actually without the two it's v sine
theta
over g
and to find a time it takes
to go from b to c
use this equation you may need to find
the height between
a and b
but if you look at the right side of the
graph between b and c
you can use the fact that h
plus y initial that's the total height
relative to the ground
is equal to one half a t squared
and if you solve for t that's going to
give you the time it takes to go from b
to c
then you add up these two values and you
should get this answer
now another thing that
you may need to know
is you need to calculate the speed just
before it hits the ground
so v x is constant it's going to be the
same at point a b and c
however v y changes
so first you need to find
v y final at point c
using v y initial at point a
once you have v y final and you already
know v x you could find v x by
using this equation
you can calculate the final speed of the
ball just before it hits the ground
using this formula
and to find the angle
use this it's inverse tangent
v y divided by v x
to find the maximum height or the height
between point a and b
you can use this equation it's
v squared
sine squared over
2g
now let's work on some problems
a ball rolls horizontally off a cliff at
20 meters per second
it takes 10 seconds for it to hit the
ground
calculate the height of the cliff and
the horizontal distance traveled by the
ball
now the first thing we need to decide
is which of the three common
trajectories do we
have so the ball
starts off on a cliff
and it rolls horizontally so it's going
to the right and eventually it's going
to fall down
so this is the type of trajectory that
we have in this problem
next
make a list of what you have
we have the speed of the ball as it
leaves a cliff
since it's traveling horizontally
we have the speed vx
so vx is equal to 20 meters per second
now it takes 10 seconds for it to hit
the ground so we have the time
calculate the height of the cliff that's
h
and the horizontal distance
traveled by the ball which is the range
to find the height of the cliff
we could simply use this equation h is
equal to one half a t squared
now a
we can use 9.8
if you use negative 9.8
h is negative but what it really means
is that the vertical displacement is
negative because the ball is going down
but
for all practical purposes we want the
height to be positive so let's plug in
positive 9.8
and t
is 10.
half of 9.8 is 4.9
10 squared is 100.
so 4.9 times 100 is 490.
so that's the height of the cliff
since it takes 10 seconds to hit the
ground
now let's calculate the range
the range is equal to v x t
and we know
v x is v cosine theta but we already
have v x which is 20.
so therefore the range
is going to be 20 meters per second
multiplied by 10 seconds
and you can see that the unit seconds
will cancel
20 times 10
is 200
so the range is 200 meters
and that's it for this problem
a ball rolls off a cliff that is 200
meters high
calculate the time it takes for the ball
to hit the ground
so for this problem
we have a similar trajectory
it rolls off the cliff
and then it hits the ground
and our goal is to find the height
and we know that the height
is one half a t squared
actually we have the height our goal is
to find the time it takes hit the ground
the height is 200.
the acceleration is 9.8
and let's solve for t
so half of 9.8
is 4.9
to isolate t squared we need to divide
both sides by 4.9
divided by 4.9
is about
40.8163
[Music]
and that's equal to t squared
so now we need to take the square root
of both sides
to get t
and so t
is going to be
6.389 seconds
and so that's how long it's going to
take
for the ball to hit the ground
a ball is released from rest and drops
straight down starting at a height of
800 meters
how long will it take to hit the ground
now what if the ball was thrown straight
down with initial speed of 30 meters per
second
how long will it take to hit the ground
now
so let's draw a picture
so let's say this is the ground level
and here we have a ball
and we're throwing it down
well for the first one it's going to be
released from rest
and it's going to fall straight down
what is the initial speed if it's
released from rest
now there's no vx component because it's
not moving to the left or to the right
it's falling straight down
so initially
v y
is equal to zero
if it's simply
if it drops down and being released from
rest
now in the other example
v y is not zero
the ball was thrown straight down
so v y
is negative 30. the speed is positive
but
the velocity is negative because it's
going in the negative y direction
in each case
the height is 800 meters
so what can we do to find the time it
takes for it to hit the ground
in the first example you can simply use
the equation h is equal to one half a t
squared
h is eight hundred
the acceleration is nine point eight
and we could solve for t
half of 9.8 is 4.9
divided by 4.9
that's
163.265
and that's equal to t squared
so now we can take the square root of
both sides to get t
so t
is 12.78 seconds
now what about part b
how can we find the time it takes for it
to hit the ground if there's an initial
speed
so recall that this equation
comes from this expression
d y
is equal to
v y initial
multiplied by t
plus one half
a y
times t squared
now we need to be careful with the way
we
are going to use this equation
we're going to put the negative signs
in the problem
so we have to be careful
using this equation we didn't have to
worry about the negative signs
now the ball is traveling 800 meters in
the negative y direction so the vertical
displacement is negative 800.
we do have an initial velocity in the y
direction it's negative 30.
so we need to take that into account
and then we have plus one half
a y the acceleration in the y direction
is negative
9.8 so this is going to be
negative 4.9
t squared
now let's move everything from the right
side to the left side
so this is going to be positive 4.9 t
squared on the left side
plus 30t
and the 800 is going to stay on the left
side so it's still negative 800.
as you can see we have a quadratic
equation in standard form to solve for t
we need to use the quadratic formula
so let's make some space first
so here's the quadratic formula t
is equal to negative b plus or minus
square root b squared
minus 4 ac
divided by 2a
so a is 4.9 b is 30 c is negative 800.
so this is going to be negative 30
plus or minus
square root 30 squared is 900
and then this is going to be minus 4
times a which is 4.9
times t squared i mean times c
which is negative 800
divided by 2a
or 2 times 4.9 which is
9.8
so now let's multiply
these three numbers
negative four times four point nine
times negative eight hundred
that's equal to positive
fifteen thousand
six hundred and eighty
and we still have a nine hundred next to
it
so now let's add
those two numbers
if we add 900 it's going to be 16 580
and the square root of that number
is 128.76
now there could be two answers
negative 30 minus 128.76
and plus 128.76
we know time can't be negative so we're
just going to ignore the negative answer
so if we take negative 30
plus 128.76
that's positive 98.76 and divided by 9.8
this will give us
a t value
of
10.08 seconds
which is less than the other answer
which was 12.78
because in the second example
the ball was thrown towards the ground
it's going to take a shorter time to get
to the ground since it was given that
initial speed
and so it makes sense why it would be
less
and we could check the answer
if you plug it into the original
equation
we need to make sure that we get 0. 4.9
times 10.08 squared
plus 30 times
10.08
that's 800.27 minus 800
that's approximately zero
so this answer is correct